A Guide to the Records of WRVA Radio Station 1925-1968
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
- Tape Recordings of Material from WRVA Archives, All tapes, with exception of no. 1, are recorded on one side only. All tapes should be played at 3 3/4 ips.
  - Tape 1
    WRVA News- Retirement of Sen. Harry F. Byrd. Includes Gov. Harrison's live announcement- Live comment: Robert Corber of State Republican Party, William Tuck's comments; Sidney Kellam's, David Satterfield of 3rd Cong. District. Gov-elect and then Lt. Gov. Mills. Godwin's comments quoted, Everett Dirkson's live comments. H.H. Humphrey quoted. Strom Thurmond quoted. Eugene McCarthy quoted as is Phillip Hart. Voice of Sen. Byrd commenting on WRVA itself.(473-603)
    WRVA News- Lengthy (24 min), obituary using many clips from their archives re Bryd's career. 1952 at U.Va. Institute of Public Affairs Byrd spoke on fiscal responsibility and on central government as threat. 1958 statement on his running again when he had not wished to. H.H. Humphrey's statement live. Governor-elect Godwin's remarks live and informal and later his formal statement. Former governors as on previous section. 1966 Oct 20 (605-943)
    Senator Byrd's denouncement of the use of Federal troops in Oxford, Miss. (946-1031)
    Walter Bishop resolution passed by the Virginia House of Delegates and Senate.(1032)
    Albertis S. Harrison's news conference, 1966 Nov 12 re the appointment of Harry S. Byrd, Jr., as U.S. Senator.(1-182)
    Walter Bishop obituary and memoir by John B. Tansey, the station manager.(182-205)
    Walter Bishop obituaries as broadcast. Various members of the staff, including John B. Tansey(206-425)
    Walter Bishop tribute from Dick Gillis Show with John B. Tansey and Calvin T. Lucy. Includes much history of station because of Bishop's lengthy connection with WRVA from the first month. Many stories, etc. (272-425)
    Testimonial dinner for Calvin Tompkins Lucy by the Va. Association of Broadcasters. Toastmaster, Ervin Kemp of the Chamber of Commerce. Mentions Lucy as 1st Pres. of VAB. Mr. W.T. Reed of Richmond (Chairman of Larus and Bros.) makes chief address. Attributes to Lucy the great ability to train his peole well and citesthe 1956 WRVA-TV which was put on the air by Lucy-trained people. Cites Lucy's independent mind; his strong belief in public service; his excellent choice of personnel, their fine training, and his willingness to leave them alone to do their jobs when trained. Mr. Lucy speaks, reminiscences about station and his experiences, with getting a liscence, with ASCAP, the United Federation of Musicians. Told stories on himself. Mentioned Ed Allen of Lynchburg, the founder of VAB in 1937. Then 11 stations (by 1961, 128 stations). Walter Bishop speaks. Gifts to Lucy, etc. 1961 Oct. 2 (426)
  - Tape 2
    T 103
    Continued testimonial dinner for C.T. Lucy. 1-18
    Gov. Albertis Harrison's news conference re pre-free schools. 1963 July 10 (20-84)
    Senator A. Willis Robertson interviewed by Joe Weeks of WRVA on inflation and the right-to-work law. (85-162)
    Ex-Gov. Albertis S. Harrison Speech on Overpopulation to the Va. Population Conference.1966 Dec 6 (164-368)
    Senator A. Willis Robertson on the Test Ban Treaty, 16 Aug. 1963. (369-472)
    Senator A. Willis Robertson I Was There Campus Life at Richmond College around 1903 (at age 16). Tell of his family background, life in Rocky Mount, Franklin Co., Va., the founding of the first high school in the county by his parents. Much railing at the slothful modern college student. He spent $250/year on his college education. Speaks of his athletic ability. The sacrifice to raise $15 to join Pi Kappa Alpha. Dr. S.C. Mitchell, Chandler and Metcalf mentioned. 1964 (late) (474-586)
    Governor A.S. Harrison News Conference. Remarks on death of Bill Thompson (WRVA staffer?). Remarks on beauties and wonders and benefits of living in Virginia. Director for the Economic Opportunity Act (Poverty Program) in Va. Sales Taxes. Chicken import quotas. Reapportionment. This conference breaks off abruptly.(687-1006)
    Ex-Governor A.S. Harrison News Conference. Political statements re Sen. Byrd, Jr., Conservatives, Democrats, etc., for the primary election of Byrd and A.W. Robertson. Appointment of Harry F. Byrd, Jr. to U.S. Senate. Continued on next reel. (1007-A8512)
  - Tape 3
    T104
    Ex-Governor A.S. Harrison news conference continued from Reel 2. Discussion about who should vote in primary; (should conservative Republicans vote in primary to insure Byrd-Robinson win?) Reporters press him hard on legal aspects. [1966] June 23 (1-35)
    WRVA Corn Cob Pipe Club, 1933. One of the acts is a bit of doggerel about E.A. Poe and his Raven. Some music, Chinese Breakdown by the Old Timers, and vocal of I'm Sitting on Top of the World by the main announcer. (38-120)
    J. Vaughn Gary introduced by Walter Bishop thanking citizens of 3rd District for an election victory 1962 Nov 6 (121-148) no.7937
    40th Anniversary Pepsi Jingle- re-recorded from 1937, the first singing commercial for radio.(149-157)
    Events of 1964 - Year of the Crumbling Walls. 1964 March 12 (160-777)
    Appomattox Ceremony of 1950 as re-broadcast 1963, with Douglas Southall Freeman's address, 1950, at dedication of the McClain house at Appamattox. 1963 April 9 (778-984)14 min 30 sec. no. A7047
    J. Vaughan Gary's resignation announcement and news conference. Questions on run-off election laws. Supports Lyndon Johnson. 1964 Feb 29 (985 to end)
    Agency Day at the WRVA transmitter. One of 57 U.S. AM stations at 50,000 watts - of 3600 AM stations in U.S. 1961? (1-122)
    J. Vaughan Gary's last report (no. 535) to the people of the 3rd Va. Congressional District. 1964 Aug 22(122-222)
    WRVA's Open for Opinion on the loss of the Lyric Theater (torn down to make room for a new building for the Life Insurance Company of Virginia), conducted by Frank Brooks. Guest is George W. Anderson, president of Lyric Theater Corp. The Lyric was used by WRVA Radio for years for such programs as the Old Dominion Barn Dance, but the building was owned by the Life Insurance Company of Virginia, and came down ending much of the amateur theater in Richmond. (223-664)